<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A peaceable and friendly address to the non-conformists: written upon their desiring an act of toleration without the sacramental test.</title>
            <author>Synge, Edward, 1659-1741.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B10107</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80924259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6381</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184783</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80924259</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80924259</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192060</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B10107)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192060)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2899:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A peaceable and friendly address to the non-conformists: written upon their desiring an act of toleration without the sacramental test.</title>
                  <author>Synge, Edward, 1659-1741.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at the Post-Office-Coffee-House in Fish-Shamble Street, for John Foster ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>P. 1 misnumbered 7.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland) Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religious tolerance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Religion --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:192060:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Peaceable and Friendly ADDRESS TO THE <hi>Non-Conformiſts:</hi> Written upon their deſiring An Act of TOLERATION Without The <hi>Sacramental Teſt,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>DUBLIN, Printed at the <hi>Poſt-Office-Coffee-Houſe</hi> in <hi>Fiſh-Shamble-Street,</hi> for <hi>John Foſter,</hi> Bookſeller, at the Sign of the <hi>Dolphin</hi> in <hi>Skinner-Row,</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:192060:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <p>Hoc Scriptum, cui Titulus, <hi>A Peaceable and Friendly Addreſs to the Non-Conformiſts, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July 19. 1697.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Narciſſus Dublin,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:192060:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To His Grace the Lord Primate of IRELAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe hope which I have of doing ſome good, or at leaſt, the confidence that I ſhall do no hurt in Publiſhing this ſmall Piece, has induced me to expoſe both it and my ſelf to the cenſure of the <hi>world.</hi> And altho there may be nothing elſe in it which may recommend it to <hi>your</hi> Grace, yet I aſſure my ſelf <hi>You</hi> will approve of that temper and calmneſs which I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured with all care to preſerve in every period of it. For, as bitterneſs, or ſharpneſs of ſtyle is contrary to Charity, no leſs than mirth and drollery in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> are to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs of Chriſtianity; ſo have I ever obſerved, that ſuch a ſatyrical way of writing is much more effectual to raiſe the Paſſion, than to convince the Judgment of an Adverſary. For which reaſon I have been ſtudiouſly careful to avoid all expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which might exaſperate, or give offence to our <hi>Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming</hi> Brethren; and ſhall, with God's Bleſſing, continue the ſame care, if ever there be an occaſion for me any further to defend what I have here written.</p>
            <p>And upon this occaſion, I beſeech your Grace to give me leave to remember to the World how Eminent an Example of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Moderation You have conſtantly ſhewn Your ſelf, as to all others, and at all times, ſo particularly to thoſe to whom I now am about to Addreſs my ſelf. No man could be more true and firm to the Eſtabliſhed Church, and at the ſame time more mild and gentle to thoſe who diſſent from her, than <hi>Your Grace</hi> has always been. Of which, <hi>Your</hi> unbyaſſed Steadineſs through all changes and viciſſitudes; together with the great
<pb facs="tcp:192060:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>lenity even in thoſe times when it was most in your Grace's power to have uſed ſeverity towards them, is a demonſtration beyond all exception.</p>
            <p>Nor can I omit to take notice of the admirable good effect which your moderate way of Dealing with ſuch perſons has had upon divers of the Non-conforming Miniſters, who were in theſe parts at the time when your Grace formerly ſate in the Chair of this Dioceſs; ſeveral of whom, (as I have been infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) being not only convinced by the Arguments, but even won by your Obliging and Chriſtian temper, did freely and readily yield to receive Ordination at your Grace's hands, according to the form preſcribed by our Church; and continued ever after to conform to the worſhip and diſcipline of it.</p>
            <p>Nor have I any thing elſe to excuſe my preſumption in this Dedication, but only the hope that your Grace will be ready, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your accuſtomed Candour, to approve of, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage every man, tho in the meanest ſtation, who endeavors, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his capacity, to follow any part of that excellent pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern which Your Grace for ſo many years has ſet to the World.</p>
            <p>That Your Grace may enjoy all the Happineſs of this Life, until ſuch time as You ſhall exchange it for a Crown of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Glory, Is the moſt earneſt and hearty Prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Cork, <date>July <hi>15. 1697.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Grace's Moſt Obedient Chaplain, And moſt Obliged Humble Servant, <hi>EDW. SYNGE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:192060:3"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THe following Addreſs was Written in the year 1695, upon occaſion of ſome Papers, which a little before had paſt between the Eſtabliſh'd Church, and Proteſtant Diſſenting Party, in Reference to a Bill of Indulgence, then under conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in, or ready (as was ſuppos'd) to be brought into the <hi>Houſe of Commons:</hi> Which Controverſy having been for ſome time ſilenced, by the frequent Adjournment of both Houſes of Parliament, it was thought unſeaſonable to Publiſh any thing in that Interval, which might relate to it: But becauſe it is not improbable, but that our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Brethren will, now the Parliament meets again, endeavour to gain the ſame Point which before they aim'd at; it is hoped that thoſe Papers may at leaſt be as ſeaſonable now, as they would have been, had they been Publiſh'd at the time when they were Written.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:192060:4"/>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:192060:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Peaceable and Friendly Addreſs <hi>To the Non-Conformiſts.</hi> Written upon their Deſiring <hi>An Act of Toleration without the Sacramental Teſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SInce it is the Duty of every Chriſtian to promote the Peace and Unity of the Church, and heartily to endeavour that there may be <hi>no Diviſions amongſt us;</hi> but that we may be <hi>perfectly joined together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>In one ſpirit, and with one mind, ſtriving together for the faith of the Goſpel, Phil.</hi> 1.27. And ſince, when one party of Chriſtians ſeparate from another, it muſt either be for a juſt cauſe, or without a juſt cauſe; it will follow, that where-ever there is Schiſm in any Church, and one Congregation ſet up in oppoſition to another, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to join in Communion with the other, there muſt, of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, be a ſin either on the one ſide or the other; either in them who give the others a juſt ground of ſeparation, or in them who ſeparate without a juſt ground.</p>
            <p>That there is a ſeparation between you and us, and thereby a Schiſm made in our National Church, is too apparent; but where the ſin of this Diviſion lies, whether upon u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, for giving you a juſt cauſe of dividing, or upon you for ſeparating from us without any ſuch cauſe; this is what on both ſides we ought to enquire after, and to reform it where ever we find it. And in order to the making of this diſcovery, I do (as I truſt, in the fear of God, and in a true ſpirit of Meekneſs and Charity) beſeech you all calmly and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to weigh and conſider theſe following things which I offer unto you.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Is there any of thoſe things which are neceſſary to the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of a Chriſtian, wanting in the Communion of our Church? Do we not profeſs and teach the true Chriſtian Faith in all its funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:192060:5"/>Articles? And if ſome of our Divines do perhaps differ from yours in the determination, or rather the manner of expreſſing of ſome Theological Points; will any one venture to ſay, that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit belief of ſuch Doctrines in difference, is abſolutely neceſſary unto Salvation? Do we not require all men to lead vertuous and holy lives? And is any part of Chriſt's Inſtitution omitted by us in the Adminiſtration either of Baptiſm or the Lord's Supper? Or what is there more required by God, in order to any man's Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than a true Faith, an holy Life, to be admitted into the Church by Baptiſm, and to own our Communion with it by the frequent participation of the Lord's Supper? In ſhort, if we are deficient in any thing which is neceſſary to Salvation, let us know what it is that is wanting amongſt us, and let the neceſſity of it be proved, and then if we receive it not, the Sin is ours.</p>
            <p>Secondly, is there any thing required by us from thoſe who Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with us, which is a Sin, and therefore not to be practiſed with a good Conſcience? However unneceſſary or impertinent any thing may be eſteemed, yet nothing is to be looked upon as a Sin but what is contrary to the Law of God: Are then any of our Conſtitutions contrary to God's Law? Or has God any where for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid us to uſe the Sign of the Croſs after Baptiſm, a Ring in the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of Marriage, a Surplice in Divine Service, the poſture of kneeling at the reception of the Lord's Supper, or any of thoſe Rites and Ceremonies which are appointed to be uſed amongſt us? And can any thing be called a Sin which God has no where forbid? But if you ſhall ſay, that tho the bare uſe of theſe things is not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, yet we uſe them after a ſuperſtitious manner, whereby they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſinful. I intreat you to conſider that we have ſufficiently declared, that we place no holineſs in any ſuch things as theſe, (wherein our Superſtition, if any there were, could only conſiſt) but that we only uſe them as things in themſelves indifferent, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by human Authority for decency and order, and at any time alterable by the ſame or the like Authority that appointed them. To conclude this Point, either ſuch things as are indifferent in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, may poſſibly be uſed without Superſtition, as Circumſtances in the worſhip of God, or elſe it will ſcarce be poſſible to perform any outward Worſhip at all without Superſtition: For outward
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192060:5"/>Worſhip cannot be performed without Outward Circumſtances; And no Man ſure will pretend that all the Outward Circumſtances of Worſhip are preſcribed or regulated by God himſelf. Since then our Rites and Ceremonies of Religion are things in themſelves indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, and therefore ſuch as may be uſed, without Superſtition, do you your ſelves teach us how we ſhall more effectually diſclaim all Superſtition, in the uſe of them, than we already do: And if we give you not ſatisfaction in the matter, the fault is juſtly ours. But to charge us with Superſtition in the uſe of thoſe things which do not neceſſarily imply that ſin in themſelves, and that at the ſame time, when we do poſitively renounce, not only the Name of Superſtition, but alſo the thing it ſelf; In my poor opinion, is not ſo agreeable unto Chriſtian Charity, which <hi>believeth all things,</hi> and <hi>hopeth all things,</hi> 1 Cor 13.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If then in the Communion of our Church there be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any thing wanting which is neceſſary to Salvation, nor, on the other ſide, any thing preſcribed in it which is ſinful; does it not apparently follow from hence that our Communion is at leaſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent? And that any Chriſtian may, with a good Conſcience, join with us in God's Worſhip and Sacraments, ſince thereby he needs not involve himſelf in any ſin, either of Commiſſion or Omiſſion. If you ſhall ſay that our Communion, tho' to us, who are perſuaded of the Lawfulneſs of it, it may be innocent; yet to you would be ſinful; becauſe ſome of you judge it abſolutely unlawfull to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with us (and no Man ought to act directly againſt his own Conſcience) and others of you do, at leaſt, doubt whether it be lawful or not; Whereas in ſuch Caſes as theſe, every man ought to <hi>be fully perſuaded in his own mind,</hi> Ro. 14.5. And <hi>he that doubteth is damned if he</hi> Conform, as well as if he <hi>eat, becauſe he</hi> Conformeth <hi>not of Faith</hi> (that is to ſay, is not throughly perſuaded of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of what he does) <hi>for whatſoever is not of Faith is Sin,</hi> v. 23. To thoſe who judge our Communion unlawful, I muſt again urge what I have already ſaid in the two preceding Paragraphs, and tell them that their Judgment in this is not only falſe, but alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently uncharitable, except they can ſhew either that ſomething is wanting, and not to be had in our Church, which yet God has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; or ſomething appointed and required which God has for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:192060:6"/>for nothing can be abſolutely ſinful and unlawful, except it be to omit the one, or to do the other. But as for thoſe who only doubt, that is to ſay, are not well aſſured, whether it be lawful to Conform to our Communion or not: If they are not able by any means to clear their doubts, and ſatisfie their Scruples; yet ſurely, in ſuch a Caſe, they ought to chooſe that way which is moſt ſafe, and free from the danger of ſin; and if there be a plain and evident Law of God which direct; them one way, they ought not to forſake that way, and go another, upon ſuch ſuggeſtions as they own to be but obſcure and doubtful. Now, what can be more evidently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, than that we ſhould ſeek and promote the Peace and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Church (as I have ſaid at the beginning of this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs). And that we ſhould give obedience unto the commands of lawful Authority, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. But, on the other ſide, the caſe in hand ſuppoſes a man to be only doubtful (and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved either way) whether it be lawful to conform to the Rites and Ceremonies by Law Eſtabliſhed in our Church; Now, if, after a reaſonable time for enquiry, he is not able to determine this doubt, ſo as poſitively to ſatisfy himſelf upon ſolid grounds, that ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity is unlawful; what reaſon can be given why ſuch a doubt (which probably may be the effect of his fancy, or prejudice only, and not of any ſober and impartial reaſoning, becauſe it never comes to a determination) ſhould be put in the ballance againſt thoſe plain commands of God which I have mentioned: And as long as ſuch a man remains doubtful as to both ſides, why may not the above ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected words of St. <hi>Paul</hi> be more ſtrongly urged for Conformity than againſt it? For why ſhould a man refuſe to conform, if he be <hi>only</hi> doubtful, and not <hi>fully perſwaded in his own mind,</hi> that he ought not to conform? And why may I not ſay, that <hi>he that doubteth is damned, if he</hi> refuſeth conformity, rather than if he conform? <hi>becauſe he</hi> refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>not of Faith;</hi> (that is to ſay, is not throughly perſwaded of the lawfulneſs of ſuch a refuſal; there being two plain Laws of God which direct him to conform, and nothing but a doubt, which is raiſed but upon obſcure grounds, that reſtrains him from it) <hi>for whatſoever is not of Faith</hi> (whether it be an action, or a refuſal) <hi>is ſin.</hi> But if you ſhall ſay, that to impoſe ſuch things upon you in the worſhip and ſervice of God, as are in themſelves indifferent,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:192060:6"/>and not commanded by any law of God, is an infringement of your Chriſtian liberty; which you are bound not to yield or give way to, but to <hi>ſtand faſt in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made you free; Gal.</hi> 5.1. I anſwer, that if any Church ſhould offer to impoſe the belief or practice of any thing, <hi>as an eſſential part of Religion, and neceſſary to Salvation,</hi> which God hath not particularly required; Againſt ſuch an Impoſition as this every Chriſtian ought to ſtand up, and aſſert his Chriſtian liberty; as the Apoſtles did againſt the Jewiſh Ceremonies, which ſome would have impoſed upon the Church as abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.1. And this is what the Apoſtle exhorts the Galatians unto; and is, as far as I can underſtand, the true notion of Chriſtian liberty, as it is ſtated in the holy Scriptures: For if way ſhould be given to ſuch ſort of Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions as theſe; in proceſs of time ſo many things (through the pride and vanity of ſome, and the ignorance and miſtakes of others) might come to be introduced into the Chriſtian Religion, as might render it (as the Jewiſh was) a yoke too heavy to be born, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10. But to plead Chriſtian liberty as an exemption from ſuch Laws and Rules which an Eſtabliſhed Church ſhall think fit to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout things, in themſelves profeſſedly indifferent, and only for order and regularities ſake; as it has no foundation that I can find either in Scripture or Reaſon; ſo the apparent conſequence of it muſt be, not that decency and order which St. <hi>Paul</hi> directs the Church to provide for in the ſervice of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. (which cannot be maintained without ſome eſtabliſhed Rules in circumſtantial mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters). But, on the contrary, that diſorder and confuſion which we may imagin muſt be in ſuch an Aſſembly, where every man ſhall eſteem it unlawful to demean himſelf according to any human pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Rules; and where therefore every the moſt ignorant perſon will be guided by nothing but the ſuggeſtions of his own thoughts, in all ſuch things as God himſelf has not particularly determined: For the avoiding of which confuſion and irregularity, every ſettled Church has always found it neceſſary to follow that direction which St. <hi>Paul</hi> long ſince gave; and to make and preſcribe certain Rules for the eſtabliſhment of <hi>Decency and Order</hi> in their Congregations. And if our Liturgy be an infringement of Chriſtian Liberty, not only all other Churches are guilty of the ſame, but even your own
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:192060:7"/>Directory, which impoſes ſome things which in themſelves are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, cannot be excuſed from it. And if you ſhall ſay that our Ceremonies are too numerous and burthenſome, beſides that others who perhaps may be as competent Judges, are of another opinion: If this were really ſo, yet the moſt it would amount to, would be only an inconvenience, (of which hereafter) and not a ſin. And tho St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> complained of the number and burden of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in his time; yet we never find that he looked upon that as any cauſe for ſeparating from the Eſtabliſhed Church. And laſtly, If you ſhall ſay that many of our Rites and Ceremonies are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unneceſſary, and that the Governors of a Church ought not to lay unneceſſary impoſitions upon the people; beſides that what ſome may think unneceſſary, others may judge to be expedient. Let us ſuppoſe that our Governors were guilty of a fault in impoſing ſome needleſs things upon us, yet will it not follow that our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance even with ſuch things, for Peace and Unity's ſake, would be any Sin, but rather, I think, a vertue: And therefore upon the whole, I cannot but conclude, that any good Chriſtian may, at leaſt very innocently, join himſelf to the Communion of our Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Then if the Communion of our Church be Lawful and Innocent in its ſelf; what imaginable reaſon can there be why you ſhould refuſe to join with us in it? For ſure you do not think that every Man is at his free Liberty, either to join himſelf to the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Church of a place, or to ſet up a diſtinct Church for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, for this would be the way not only to divide, but crumble the Church; till the different fancies of Men ſhould bring it to nothing. And if you ſhall tell us that ſome of our Conſtitutions are not ſo conveniently ſettled, as they ſhould be for promoting the Glory of God, and the Practice of Piety; Beſides that there never was any Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Appointment ſo perfect as to be free from all defect and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience; And that what may ſeem inconvenient to one, may perhaps be thought convenient by another (there being ſcarce any particular Rules of convenience ſo fixed, but what will be different<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thought of by different Men, according to the diverſity of their Apprehenſions and Circumſtances). I deſire to know whether one or more bare inconveniences, which yet are, or may be, free from ſin, can be a ſufficient reaſon to ſeparate from an Eſtabliſhed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192060:7"/>Church? And if ſo, what Church is there upon the face of the Earth from which this principle will not juſtifie a Diviſion? It is indeed the duty of every Man ſoberly and peaceably to ſeek for the Rectifying, even any inconveniencies which he perceives to be in the Church: But ſince it is a Rule of Charity that it <hi>beareth all things, endureth all things, ſuffereth long, is not eaſily provoked,</hi> and <hi>ſeeketh not her own,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13, 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Methinks every good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhould be contented to bear, even with many inconveniencies (untill ſuch time as God ſhould touch the hearts of thoſe in whoſe power it ſhould be to remedy them) rather than occaſion a Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the Church, which, beſides the ſin, is certainly a greater inconvenience than all thoſe which you can complain of put together. But if you ſhall ſay that you find your ſelves more Edified in Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Piety by your own Meetings, than by frequenting our Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies; Not to aſcribe this to your prejudice and prepoſſeſſion, nor to make any compariſons which may ſeem odious, or may tend to exaſperate; I ſhall only tell you if this be a real truth, and not a bare fancy only; it may ſeem to be a reaſon why you ſhould hold ſome Aſſemblies, beſides the Parochial Congregations, for your mutual Edification, and to provoke others to emulation; which might be a means to promote a general reformation of all neglects or diſorders in the Church, (provided that nothing were therein ſaid or done which might give any of your own members or others, a juſt occaſion to look upon you as a ſeparate Church ſet up in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and not in ſubordination to the eſtabliſh'd one). But what reaſon you can ground upon this for a down-right ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and an utter refuſal of our Communion; I confeſs I am not able to find. But if you ſhall ſay that you do not abſolutely ſeparate from us, nor utterly renounce our Communion, but that you ſometimes come to our publick Worſhip, and receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord's Supper after our preſcribed Form, which is by ſome of you aſſerted and pleaded for under the name of occaſional Communion; I deſire to be informed, if occaſional Communion with us be lawful, why ſhould conſtant Communion with us be thought unlawful? If it be a ſin to join with us in God's Worſhip and Sacraments, it ought not to be done ſo much as once; but if it be no ſin, why may it not be done always? And would it not be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:192060:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>much more agreeable to the temper of Chriſtianity, and the Spirit of Peace and Unity, for you conſtantly to frequent our Aſſemblies, who own you may lawfully do it, and to hold your own other Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings either after or before ours; rather than by holding them juſt at the ſame time with ours, to keep the people as much as you can, ſtrangers from our Congregations, than alienating their affections from us; cheriſhing an opinion in many of them, that our way of Worſhip is utterly unlawful, and widening, or at leaſt keeping open, that breach which otherwiſe in a little time, would probably cloſe, and heal of it ſelf.</p>
            <p>The deſign of what I have hitherto ſaid, has been to lay the matter home to your Conſciences, to perſwade you to embrace the Communion of our Church, and thereby ſuperſede the neceſſity of a Toleration: But if all we can ſay or argue upon this matter will not prevail, then,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> I would gladly know what it is which you aim at, and propoſe to your ſelves in an Act of Toleration? Is it only to have the liberty of Serving God in that way which you think to be beſt, and thereby to be free from perſecution, and to go the readieſt way, as you ſuppoſe, to Heaven, without let or moleſtation? Or is it to lay a foundation for the overthrow of the Eſtabliſhed Church, and to get, in time, the whole Eccleſiaſtical and Civil Power into your own hands, as is already done by thoſe of your perſuaſion in <hi>Scotland?</hi> If the latter of theſe be your deſign, ſure you muſt think us no leſs than fools and mad-men, if we give way to our own Overthrow &amp; Ruin; and do not give you all the Oppoſition that poſſibly we can; but if the former be only, and adequately your deſire, why are you ſo Zealous againſt the <hi>Sacramental Teſt</hi> (as it is called) as even to refuſe an Act of Toleration, rather then have this Clauſe inſerted in it, That no one ſhall be capable of any Office, or Employment in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth, who ſhall not ſo many times in the Year Receive the Holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper, according to the Eſtabliſhed Form? I am ſenſible, That Men may have ſtrange Notions, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices and Scruples, in matters of Religion; and that what ſeems to be the higheſt and cleareſt Reaſon to one Man, may not appear Convincing, or Concluding to another. And therefore, I do not wonder that good and well meaning Men, tho' miſtaken, ſhould
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:192060:8"/>be very earneſt for Liberty of Conſcience, to be clear from ſuch Impoſitions as they think they cannot lawfully ſubmit to, and to have the freedom of ſerving God in ſuch a way as they apprehend may be pleaſing to him. But when Men are not contented with this, except they may have alſo a ſhare in the Government, and be made capable of Employments of Power, Truſt, and Profit; I think it is very apparent, That they deſign and aim at ſome thing elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Salvation of their Souls, and freedom from Perſecution; And it becomes the Wiſdom of every Government, carefully to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider even the remote, if probable, conſequences of what they do; and however, it may be fit to deal gently with tender Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet that State which ſhall ſeem to Encourage or ſet up two ſeveral Parties, differing from each other in matters of Religion, (which ſtrangely Unites, or divides the Affections of Men) to make Factions one againſt the other, and to ſtand in perpetual di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Oppoſition and Competition one with the other for all the Places of Truſt, Power, and Profit in the Common-Wealth; I believe will be thought by moſt Wiſe Men to be out in its Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</p>
            <p>But if I am told that this laſt Queſtion which I have put, contains in it a Falſe and Uncharitable Suggeſtion againſt the <hi>Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts;</hi> and that they have no manner of Deſign againſt the preſent Eſtabliſhment of the Church, as is pretended, but only deſire to ſtand upon equal Terms with the reſt of His Majeſty's Subjects as to Civil Matters; I anſwer that, ſuppoſing all this to be True; yet no one knows but their Succeſſors, in the next Generation, may endeavour to advance a little farther than what is propoſed by their Predeceſſors in this. And ſince the Presbyterian P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rty in theſe Kingdoms did in the late Wars of 1641. actually overthrow the Eſtabliſhed Epiſcopal Church, and have never yet Publickly Renounced thoſe Principles by which they then Acted, nor Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied any Repentance for what they did. And ſince the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians of <hi>Scotland</hi> have now again Overturned the Epiſcopal Church of that Kingdom; have we not all the Reaſon that can be to fear that, tho' our preſent <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> may keep a kind and friendly Correſpondence with us; becauſe we have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lately joined againſt a common Enemy, yet in the next Generation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:192060:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Heats and Animoſities may probably ariſe between their Succeſſors and ours, which if not before hand carefully prevented, may tend to the diſturbance, or perhaps the Ruin both of Church and State: And ought not every Government to provide for Poſterity, as well as for the Preſent Generation? And thus have I Declared, or at leaſt Suggeſted, my thoughts in this great Affair, with all the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and plainneſs that I could; and I hope with that Mildneſs which becomes a peaceable Man and a Chriſtian: How far what I have ſaid may prevail upon any Man, I know not, but I hope that no one can take any Offence, either at what I have ſaid, or at the manner wherein I have expreſſed my ſelf; and if I have miſſed of that Good which I deſigned, yet at leaſt it will be ſome ſatisfaction to me, to think that I have done no hurt; and whilſt I have been Pleading for Unity, have ſaid nothing which ſhould tend to the breach of Charity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
